Hello! My name is Natalia Khokhlova
and I am a lecturer for the course “Effective team management” at ITMO University
and an experienced HR.
In this video I will present to you a brief overview of the section “Self-presentation”
within the online-course “Living in science: a young researcher's guide”.
My colleagues and I will tell you about the skills of self-presentation in this section
such as business communication and business correspondence.
In the video lecture “Ethics of the business communication”
we will learn about how to correctly choose the communication channel
in order to address your issues more effectively and to reach your objectives.
We will find out what basic rules and principles of business communication
true professionals should stick to
and what typical mistakes should be avoided.
We will surely prepare
a competent curriculum vitae together, which is your professional business card.
We will also discuss how to prepare for and properly pass an interview
to surely get the job of your dreams that best suits your needs.
In video lectures, dedicated to public speaking skills,
we will talk about how to make speech in public, how to prepare for it,
how to cope with anxiety before and during the performance.
We will talk about the goals of the presentation, target audience, genres and structure of the speech.
You will learn about nonverbal components of the speech such as voice,
mimic, gestures, hands, and so on.
In the lecture “Technique of answering questions” we will discuss
how to communicate with the audience after your presentation.
We will find out how to answer questions, including the provocative and trick ones,
how to respond to the criticism and how to answer questions you don't know the answers to for some reason.
In this same section “Self-presentation” we will deliberate
on such an interesting process as networking.
In simple terms, it’s about creating a circle of professionals around you
and building relationships with people in a way
that you will always be able to ask them for advice,
promote some of your projects or ideas
and to get some useful information in general.
My colleagues and I would be happy to share our knowledge,
skills and abilities in the field of self-presentation with you.
We are sure that this information would be useful in your professional life and beyond.
See you in our video lectures!