Hello, my name is Aleksey Slobozhanyuk,
and I am a researcher of Faculty of Physics and Engineering at ITMO University.
I and my colleague Anton Gopka,
who is the dean of Faculty of Technological Management and Innovations,
will tell you about very important part of every scientist’s life:
how to attract funds, as well as
how to make the transition from your scientific idea to the commercialization of this scientific idea.
At first, we will tell you about grants.
These are the grants which you can get on a competitive basis and implement your scientific ideas
or even create fields of research.
Then, we will tell you where a student could receive scholarships from:
about different types of scholarships, and how students can
study abroad and have an internship in the World’s leading universities.
Also Anton will tell you about how to make a step from science to commercialization.
He will tell you from what to start, how to estimate you idea,
he will share with you the technologies,
which investors would use to assess your projects.
Then he will tell you about the process of assessing ideas,
and how to present them.
He will later explain you how to make a pitch-presentation,
after which every investor would give money to your project.
We are sure that this course will help you to put into practice a lot of
your scientific ideas through raising finances,
also it will teach you the methods you will be able to use
in order to move from a scientific idea to the implementation of a final product.
Good luck in your studies!