Hello, my name is Inna Anokhina. And today we begin the substantive part of our course,
and we are going to talk about scientific publications, as it’s impossible
to imagine a modern scientist not reading or writing scientific articles.
As for the scientific text, it should be short and clear,
also from the point of view of the use of linguistic means, not to confuse the reader and not to be ambiguous.
In the modern world, all scientific articles are written according to the structure
adopted by the American National Standards Institute in 1972.
It’s interesting that the first scientific work which had an IMRAD structure
was that of Louis Pasteur. IMRAD is an abbreviation
that translates into Russian as "introduction, methods, results and discussion".
All scientific articles are written according to this structure, so today
we will consider the structure of any scientific research article.
Of course, when you see an article or start working on an article,
the first thing you think about is the title.
The title of a scientific article should not be long;
it should consist of 8-10 words, not including prepositions and conjunctions,
and attract the attention of your audience.
It is clear that in the process of working on the article,
its title may change,
however you still need to come up with a working version.
After the article, you need to specify
the author or group of co-authors of the article.
You need to specify everyone’s names, initials, titles,
degrees, places of work or study and countries.
However, be careful, because the requirements
differ from journal to journal
and before you fill out information about the author or authors,
you need to coordinate it with the requirements of the journal.
In the third place there is the abstract.
Despite the fact that the abstract comes immediately after the title
and the list of authors or the author, it is often written at the very end.
It’s created after the article is already written and the study was conducted.
The abstract is also used to attract the readers’ attention.
It is a single paragraph which consists of 250-300 words
and corresponds, in fact, to the structure
to which the article corresponds,
that is, indicates the subject and the method of the research.
Also you should not use abbreviations
and numeric values in your abstract.
Despite the fact that the abstract is in the first place, almost in the first place,
the abstract is written at the very end of the study and work.
That is this is the last part you are working on.
Then you need to formulate a list of keywords.
There should not be many keywords and should not be few.
Usually authors allocate from 4 to 8 keywords, and keywords are used
to search for your article in international publication databases.
After that the main part of the article begins.
It occupies, in general, 80 per cent of the volume
of any scientific text of this type.
And we will discuss now the introduction, methods, results and discussion.
As it is clear, the introduction introduces the reader
into the problems you are dealing with.
In the introduction, you review the literature in this field,
in the introduction, you point out those blind spots
that exist in this field or
that have not yet been investigated before you.
At the end, you formulate the purpose and objectives of your research.
Then, in the methods section, you describe the research methodology,
and describe it as carefully as you can and in great details.
The research methodology should be described in such a way
that a specialist in the field could reproduce
your experiment and get the same results
that you received in your laboratory.
It should be noted that readers are
unlikely to read this section,
because you have already mentioned in the introduction,
which method you used.
However, this section is very important, because the reviewer
will surely read it, read the methodology
and, if he has doubts about the possibility of reproducing
the experiment in the laboratory,
then your article will, at best,
be sent to you for revision,
in the worst case the publication will be rejected.
The next section that we will discuss with you
is the results section.
Here you describe the results
of your experiment and present them in the form of tables,
graphs, diagrams, photographs and drawings.
You describe the results, compare, and give a brief comment.
The next section is the discussion.
If the previous section dealt with facts,
this section deals with ideas.
You describe your idea, you relate
the results to your hypothesis, and you talk about
whether you have achieved your goal and whether the tasks have been completed.
You can also mention limiting factors.
As a matter of fact, this section is a generalization
of all your work on the one hand.
And on the other hand, it is this section
that connects your own results, which you received
as a result of the experiment with the real world,
with the fact where and how the results
of your research can be applied.
After you give the prospect for
future research in the discussion section,
you need to thank the organization that
may have sponsored your research, if any.
After gratitude there is a list of the used literature
in which you need to specify all the sources,
which you referred to in the text of the article.
You should be very careful again
and follow the literature list requirements of the journal,
you submit your article for the publication to.
Thus, we have considered
the structure of an article today,
and in the next lecture we will consider the process of working on a text.