We continue talking about
publications, and today
we will discuss how
to write a research
article in English.
An article in English is similar
to an engineering device,
which has a rigid structure
and each part of it
has its own function.
It is important to note that the structural
element of an article in English,
just like in Russian,
is a paragraph.
It works in the same
manner as in Russian –
one idea is
one paragraph.
One paragraph contains an
introduction that is followed by
informational sentences, which
confirm the introduction and
present examples, and a
closing phrase.
Sentences in English
language should not be
longer than 10-12 words,
they should not be long.
If you are not an English
native speaker, this
will help you, first of all,
not to lose your idea, be
clear with what you want to say.
On the other hand, it will
let you think of the reader
that you are writing for.
Clearly, nowadays English
is a global language for the
whole international community of
scientists and researchers,
this is why your publication may
be read by a Chinese, Spaniard,
Frenchman, or Italian, and you
should make sure that they can
understand your research
and scientific results.
This is why your thought
should be expressed accurately
and clearly in 10-12 words.
Now, we should discuss lexical
and grammatical linguistic
means that will help
you in writing
articles in English.
First of all,
it is the voice.
Today there is a tendency in
English for academic purposes
that suggests us to choose
active voice instead
of passive one.
In fact,
this enables
you to take responsibility
for your research and
for the report
that you
present in
your publication.
To put it differently,
active voice helps you to
claim that you are the author
of this particular research.
It does not mean that you
cannot or should not use
passive voice
at all.
Passive voice is very
useful in such chapters
as methods and results,
where you present how
your experiment proceeded,
and the findings
that you obtained.
Concerning
tenses:
their use in Academic
English is limited.
As a rule, you use
only five tenses:
present simple, past simple, present continuous,
past continuous and present perfect.
Future simple is sometimes
used as well, especially
in Conclusion chapter.
However, the meaning that
future simple gives to a
statement is quite
fuzzy and inexact.
This is why, other
lexical and grammatical
constructs should be preferred to
future simple when describing
your plans for the future.
As far as present perfect is
concerned, you can use
this tense when you state
what you have done, which
methods you have used, what
results you have gained,
as well as in conclusion
when you should present
your findings.
While working on an article
text, reading it over
and over again, you should get
rid of all lexical items
that are frequently repeated.
You can highlight
all repeating
words with a highlighter.
This way, firstly, you will
understand how many
repetitions you have.
Secondly, you will find
parts the text that need to
be rephrased and extra words
that should be deleted.
I want to mention
specifically frequent use of
“of” preposition by
Russian native speakers.
Its active use is conditioned
by our mother tongue, but in
order to make the text sound
good in English, you should
use “of”
rarely.
You can use a color highlighter
again in order to find all
the phrases with “of”
and check where you can
change it with a
chains of nouns.
A chain of nouns is
a phrase that contains
two-three-four nouns
without prepositions.
It is often used
in academic English,
and is a good substitution
for preposition “of”.
ТI also want to note that
the more you read
the better you write.
When you read articles in
your scientific field, you learn
specific terms,
to begin with.
Secondly, you see language
patterns and phrases that
other authors use in their
publications, and you can add
them to your works.
How to do it?
You should take two or
three different highlighters;
Underline, for example, with
pink all lexical items
and phrases that are you
are familiar with, but you
forget to use them in
your texts for some
reason.
Use yellow highlighter for the
new words and phrases
that you would start
use in your works.
And you can underline
with blue all
useful terms.
I think this can be very
useful for your work on
the text and content
of your article.
These are just common rules
and recommendations for
writing articles in
English.
However, the rules
exist to be broken.
For example, subjunctive mood
is not recommended to be
used in scientific articles,
but if you want to write
about some results that
you could potentially obtain,
but have not, you
can use subjunctive
mood.
The important part here is that
you and your reader should
understand why you do it.
You may find other recommendations
on writing articles in English
in supplementary
materials for
the course.