Hello!
My name is Oleg Borisov.
In previous lectures, my colleague
Inna Anokhina discussed
what publications are, their
structure and the rules of
writing articles.
In this and following
lectures, you will learn about
a very convenient
tool for preparing articles –
the LaTeX publishing
system.
I will speak about the principles of
working with this system, the main concepts
and the structure of the source files.
The basis of this tool is
the TeX desktop
publishing system, created by American
mathematician and software
engineer Donald
Knuth for typesetting of
texts with mathematical
formulas.
Later on, another American scientist
Leslie Lamport developed
his own macro-
definition package based on
this system and
named it LaTeX.
This macro-definition package is
still popular.
To start working with the LaTeX
system you will need
to install three components onto your
computer. The first component is the
TeX distribution corresponding
to the operating system (notably,
the cross-platform nature
of this tool is
its undoubted advantage);
The second is the LaTeX
file editor (Although you can
work with files in any text
editor, it is convenient
to use special programs
with syntax
highlighting provided)
the final component - is to install
a program for viewing PDF files.
Now a couple of words about the
principle of working with the system.
There are well-known
editors of the
“get what I see” type, in which the
process of preparing the document
involves working directly
with the final file. For example,
editing is performed in parallel
with viewing the result.
In the LaTeX system, working with a
document (its source file)
and viewing the final
file are two different
operations, performed sequentially.
First, the source file
is compiled in tex format.
It includes the content of the
document, as well as
the command set that
define how the text
should look like.
After compilation, the file
of the final document is
generated in PDF format with
the required formatting.
On the one hand, this principle
will require initial training,
as it involves prior knowledge
of the commands and possession
ofsystem syntax, but
on the other hand, it
significantly speeds up
the layout process.
Next, let us consider
what the source
file is. It consists
of two parts – the preamble
and the body of the document.
The preamble sets up
different packages, overriding,
settings, options
that affect
the entire document.
The body contains the content
of the document in
accordance to the system syntax.
When working with the source
file, as noted above, it is
necessary to operate
on various commands.
They are declared through the
backslash character followed by
the name of the command without
spacing.
For some commands, it is necessary
to specify arguments, which
can be mandatory
and indicated
in braces
or indicated
in square brackets.
For example, the first command
starting the preamble
of the source tex
file is as follows.
It determines the
style of the document.
Notice the backslash
character, the name of
the command, and the mandatory
argument – “article” specified
in braces.
This argument means that the
document, after compilation,
will be issued in the form of an article.
In addition to “article”, there are
other standard categories, such as
“book” for writing a book or
“report” for writing
a report.
It is important to note that
the category can be non-standard.
For instance, to prepare
a publication for a journal or
a conference proceeding,
a special category
can be used that takes into
account the requirements
of the editorial design.
To do this, you will need to place
the file with the cls extension
downloaded from the editorial site
in the folder with the tex file.
Regarding the \documentclass
command, optional settings
can be specified in
the square brackets,
separated by commas, between
a command name and the
mandatory argument.
For example, point size,
paper format,
dual column text, etc.
The command \documentclass is
followed by connecting the packages,
depending on the
functionality required.
These packages can either be
pre-installed with the
TeX distribution or can
be downloaded from
the repository during compiled time.
The next important concept,
which is actively used while
working with LaTeX, is called
environment. It is
set using the following
construction.
Notice that there is
a mandatory argument
in the braces –
the name of the environment.
Depending on the
selected environment,
some additional arguments,
both mandatory
and optional can be specified.
Regarding the structure of
the source file, after
declaring the document style and
entire preamble, it is necessary
to define an environment that represents
the body of the document itself.
Inside we will have the
content of the document.
When typing, keep in
mind basic rules.
Words in the source file are
separated from each other
by spaces, while the number
of spaces does not matter –
when compiling, only one
will be placed between
the words.
Carrying over to the new
line is also perceived as
a space.
Paragraphs are separated
by blank lines.
After the compilation
most of the characters appear
as they appear in the source file.
An exception is the special
characters used in
the LaTeX syntax including:
backslash, braces, percentage,
underlining, circumflex,
tilde, dollar sign, hash.
To format the text
specific commands are
used, after changing
the current font settings
(e.g. point size,
style, etc.).
These changes are distributed
to the end of the current group,
which is limited to either
the current environment
or braces.
The convenience of the LaTeX system
is that many routine tasks are
automated like adding links.
When it is necessary
to refer to a specific
place in
the text,
for example,
to a sentence
or a
word on
another page,
you can use the
following commands:
\pageref{} command, which
returns to the page number,
or the \ref{} command, which
returns to the number of the
corresponding section.
The system also automizes
updates of page and chapter
numbers during compilation.
In the same way, organizes
the references in numbered
formulas, figures,
tables, etc.
At the end of this lecture,
try to create
your first document using
the example given.
Please note that by default,
the LaTeX system does
not support the Russian language.
Therefore, it is necessary
to include in the preamble
the corresponding
packages, namely
the encoding in which the Russian
text will be added.
In the next video, we will consider
a set of formulas, adding
pictures and tables
in the LaTeX system.