In the previous lecture,
we learned about the LaTeX
publishing system as a whole.
We discovered the principles
of working in this system,
the main concepts and the structure of source files.
In this lecture, we will continue to learn
about the LaTeX system by studying a set of
system by studying a set of formulas,
adding pictures and composing tables.
As mentioned in the previous
lecture, the source file contains
a preamble in
which packages are
declared depending
on their functionality.
If the document contains
a large number of formulas,
it would be advised to download
the following two packages.
The LaTeX system has a
number of different ways
to set formulas. Taking
this into account, we will
learn the main ones.
The first set of formulas
can be included in a text
or shown in
a separate line.
In the first case they
are separated on both sides
by a single dollar sign.
In the second case they are
separated with a double dollar sign.
Notice that formulas are
considered mathematical
notations, including individual
variables and symbols
within the text.
Second set of formulas
can be numbered and
unnumbered. Numbered
formulas are set using
the equation environment.
Pay close attention to the presence
of a name inside this environment.
Later on, this formula can
be referenced using the
\ref{} command with
a special label.
Unnumbered formulas can
be indicated by using
the aforementioned double
dollar sign or the same equation
environment by adding an
asterisk at the end of
a name.
It is necessary to
disable numbering.
The third is used to
obtain a sequence of formulas
using various sets that differ
in the way the formulas
are aligned with each other.
Let us take the eqnarray
environment as an example.
Ampersands are necessary
for aligning formulas
by a certain sign (in
this case, an equal sign).
Double backslash is responsible
for transferring to a new line.
Note that there are
alternative ways
to set up the same formula.
For example, an alignment of
formulas can also be indicated
by an align
environment.
Here ampersands can be used
to achieve more complex
formula alignment
with each other.
Adding an asterisk in the
end of both environments
will disable numbering.
You can also
disable numbering
by adding
the \nonumber
command to the sequence.
As for the mathematical
operators and
symbols themselves.
In the LaTeX system,
you can type
any existing operator.
During your first steps we
recommend to use guidelines
that are widely represented
on the internet.
Here are a few
examples of the most
common cases.
Subscripts and superscripts
are indicated by using the
underscore character and circumflex.
These commands, by
default, are applied only
to single characters.
If you need to specify
an index of several symbols
then it must be
enclosed in braces.
Fractions are recorded
using a slash
or the \frac{}{} command
with required arguments
that correspond to the
numerator and denominator.
The superscript is written
using the corresponding
commands before variables.
Let’s revise a few examples.
The height of brackets can
be adapted to the content
inside by using the
commands \left( and \right).
If only one bracket
(left or right) is needed, the
second one must be balanced
with a null bracket in the
\left. or \right command.
The square root is written
by using the \sqrt{} command.
In addition, an optional
argument can be specified
between the command name and
braces  to display the
degree of the root.
Matrixes are defined using
bmatrix, pmatrix and vmatrix
environments using square,
round and straight brackets,
respectively.
Sometimes, it is useful to use
an array without brackets with
the array environment.
Notice the required argument
, which determines
the number of columns and
their horizontal alignment
(in this case,
three columns
aligned to the right,
center and left).
In the LaTeX system, it is possible
to use trigonometric operators,
logarithms, limits, integrals,
partial differentiation, lowercase
and uppercase letters of
the Greek alphabet, among
others.
You can also create
your own operators
using the following command
with two mandatory arguments,
the first one being the command and
the second one being the operator.
As a task, try typing
different types of formulas in
LaTeX (included, taken out,
numbered and not numbered),
which are inherent to
your professional field.
For example, like this.
Let’s move on to adding
pictures in the LaTeX system.
For this, it is necessary to
download the following package.
Figures are added using
the following construction.
In the figure environment there is
an optional argument that determines
the location of the figure
on a page (t corresponds
to the location at the top
of the page, b - at the
bottom parts of the page, p - on a
separate page, h - at the same place
where it is declared
in the source file).
The center environment is
necessary for content alignment
surroundings in the center.
The required argument of
the \includegraphics command
is the name of the image
file, if it is located
in the same folder, as the source
file or the path to the file
in case it is
in a subfolder.
An optional argument determines
the size of the figure
(width or height), which
can be set as an absolute
value or relative
to the length lines.
The \caption{} command sets
the caption below the figure.
Links to the figure are
carried out by using the
фppropriate mark in a way that
is already familiar to us.
When adding a vector image
in eps format, it is necessary
to enable the epstopdf package,
which provides preliminary
conversion of the eps file to pdf.
Adding tables is carried
out in a similar method
by using the following construction.
The table environment
has the same optional
argument as the figure
environment to determine
the location of the table on the page.
The tabular environment requires
an argument that determines
the number of columns,
alignment settings and
presence of vertical
boundaries of the barrels.
Horizontal boundaries in the
table are drawn using the
\hline command.
At the end of this
lesson, practice
adding charts, diagrams,
raster and vector figures
in tex file. As well
as in the preparation
of tables according to the
example above. In the next
lecture we will consider
a number of useful options
that will be an advantage to know,
while working with the system.