Hello.
This lecture will be devoted to scientometric indicators of journals.
First attempts to make use  of scientometrics, use
citations in work of scientific and research organizations
were made in 1927, while gathering librarian collections
of some universities.
This whole system is based on the assumption that if some
articles are cited more often than others, they have
better quality. And if these
frequently cited articles get into a journal, this means that
the quality of this journal is much higher than
that of other journal in this subject area.
First and the most well-knownindicator
that is used for journals’ evaluation
is Impact factor.
I want to emphasize that real Impact factor may be
calculated only for the journals included in Web of Science system.
Why?
Because Web of Science has rights on the word
brand “Impact factor”, that’s why.
How is Impact factor calculated? Impact factor is a number of
citations made in a particular year
of the articles published in this journal
during previous two years, divided by total number of articles
over the same period of time. Impact factor cannot be used
to compare journals from different scientific areas
because of the following reasons:
- Different publication activity in different areas
- Different number of researchers
- And simply because of difference in frequency of documents publishing
In addition to the classical Impact factor, that includes
information about a two-year period,
there is so called five-year impact factor.
These two indicators are in constant rivalry, trying
to prove which one is more accurate.
In fact, the two-year Impact factor allows making operations
more frequently, which is logical, while the five-year one
includes more samples, and shows
more qualitative evaluation of a journal.
In Scopus system there is CiteScore, which is
Impact factor’s analog. It is calculated in exactly
the same way – it is a correlation between the citations
in a particular year and the number of articles
in this journal over the previous three years.
The only difference is the number of years
that is taken for the analysis –
two years for Impact factor,
and three years for CiteScore.
It is important to note that both Impact factor and CiteScore
are calculated for the previous year or the year before last.
This is done to avoid risk of missing citations
that were made during current year,
but have not been indexed just yet, or have not been made
during current calendar year.
Another important indicatoris SNIP, Source normalized impact per paper.
What does it allow to do? It helps in situations?
when neither classical Impact factor nor CiteScore work,
in particular it allows to compare journals from different
subject areas.
How is it possible?
It is possible because SNIP considers size of
the subject area, number of researchers
working in this area, as well as potential citations,
meaning the assumption on how many citations an article
devoted to one or another issue can potentially get.
Another important metrics is Eigenfactor or so called
prestige factor.
It has the iterative model in its basis, similar to that
used by Google Pagerank, created by Larry Page.
As soon as you type in your retrieval request in Google,
the links get arranged in certain order:
first ones are considered to be the most reliable,
popular or prestigious. If we imagine it as
a comprehensible model,
it would work the following way: if your article was cited
in Nature and in some random journal of
a regional university,  he former citation would
weight way more.
It might weight hundred or even thousand times more.
SJR is calculated on the basis of Scopus databases,
and has its own portal that shows ranking of all journals
included in Scopus, as well
as rakings of countries, universities
and even separate research groups.
Not only SJR is published on a  separate portal where you can
find rankings of journals, countries and universities,
evaluated on the basis of
this indicator, it is also used for determination of
journals’ quartile. There are four journal quartile
s in Scopus and Web of Science The most well-known and popular
articles are published in the first quartile,
while the least popular ones - in the fourth quartile respectively.
In Scopus system we would use CiteScore for this ranking,
while in Web of Science
we would use Impact factor for this.
In addition to classical indicators,
there are several alternative ones, so called “alt metrics”.
In fact, they are references to a scientific work,
published in a scientific journal, but references made
in popular public and political media, or in social networks,
such as Twitter, Facebook, LinkedIn, and what not.
In this context, there is such an interesting thing
as NY Times scientific citation index.
When in Sunday scientific column of NY Times
the review on a scientific research is published,
its scientometric indicators  ise considerably, which confirms
that public interest to one or another scientific issue,
one or another scientific article,
may have serious influence  on academia and career of
an individual scientist. Nonetheless, in spite of
the fact that scientometric indicators are relatively
established procedure for evaluation of scientific work,
potential of a research, as well as career of individual
scientists, one should use them with great caution, and
remember that citation indicators, H-indices, and impact factors
do not always give an accurate evaluation of
a work’s quality.