Hello, I am Iliya Kuftiryov. Today we will talk about rankings.
Rankings are a very popular topic nowadays.
And in this module I would like to tell you about universities’ rankings.
Of course, it is impossible to discuss all existing rankings.
There are several dozens of rankings in the world.
This is why I would like to point our three main academic rankings.
These are QS ranking, Times Higher Education ranking,
both of them are originally British,
and another one is Shanghai Ranking, which is also called Academic Ranking of World Universities.
All three rankings are international and world-wide, but they have different goals and objectives.
They are very popular recently, and I am sure that university applicants, including those in Russia,
take these rankings into consideration when making decision about which university to choose.
Also, the government decides how to support universities,
based on their positions in rankings.
For you to feel more confident in the topic,
I want to tell you right away that information on which indicators form methodology of these
three rankings you can find in the supplementary files for the module.
In order not to consider every indicator in details, as it would have been a very boring story,
I would like to gather all indicators of academic rankings in three groups.
One of these groups is directly related to soft skills.
Ranking agency takes the information, let’s say,
from the official website of a university, and based on this it calculates some indicators.
For example, percentage of foreign students, percentage of foreign professors,
and this way the agency uses these results for making ranking tables.
Alternatively, the university gives this
information and statistics itself, and the results are calculated the same way.
The second group is so called scientometric indicators.
In particular, let’s consider citations indicator, which is called Hirsch index,
my colleague Daniil Shirokov has already told you about Hirsch index.
So in QS and Times Higher Education the citation indicator,
which is a normalized citation indicator, is used.
This indicator takes into consideration publication type, scientific field and year of publication –
all these parameters are taken into account in rankings.
And finally, the third group of indicators, the one that is related
to soft skills, is so called reputational indicators.
For example, in QS ranking, recognizability of a university makes
up to 50% of the final result.
Let’s note this once again, 50% of the result that a university gets in the
ranking is determined by its reputation and recognizability.
In Times Higher Education ranking it makes up approximately 1/3 of the result.
In Shanghai ranking there is no reputation indicator, but there are others
that you can check, and they are not directly related to reputation.
Here is the second aspect – what is the connection between the university’s reputation, its recognizability and your soft skills.
You may be surprised, but it is not direct, of course, it is not functional,
but I would say, there is correlation, and quite a strong one.
Look what I mean.
I hope that you are not in the very beginning of your way, but you have already
started your scientific research, and have written your scientific publication.
When it is published, it is not the end of the way,
you should keep promoting the results of your research,
visit scientific conferences, participate in international networking,
present these results to your colleagues, to other research groups,
be involved into academic community, scientific community,
a part of which every scientists wants to be,
especially now, in our small world, where everyone knows each other,
if we are talking about one sphere, everyone communicates with each other actively,
but this is that very community where, I am sure, you will find your well-deserved place.
Speaking about communicative skills, that is a part of soft skills,
speaking about the possibility and necessity to talk about your scientific results,
disseminate them, present to the public, these are your actions
that in the end of the day will make you organization,
your university more recognizable,
people will become better familiarized with what you do,
and you can expect that when they participate in the expert survey,
held by both QS and Times Higher Education, possibly these people,
who know you and the results of your research, will tell the whole world that your
university and your research group, having particularly you in mind,
they will tell the world that this university is advanced
in this or that field of scientific research.
This is why you should not neglect these opportunities, do share your findings, share your discoveries,
participate actively in international networking,
and in the long run it will influence the ranking position of your university.
To conclude I would like to note that, of course, rankings
facilitate the university brand forming and developing.
Perhaps, someone will see the reverse logic in here.
Universities are fully developed brands, and this is why they have good positions in rankings,
but it is not the causality that matters here, but the fact
that thanks to the university you get a unique opportunity to
develop, improve and make more recognizable your own
scientific brand, your own scientific style.
I wish you success in this, and do read the rankings, study the rankings and develop your soft skills!