Dear students, we have already learned
different time and energy management
techniques.
Today I want to talk to you
about attention management.
Harvard university psychologists have
conducted some research, the results of
which show, that we spend 47% of awake
time dreaming.
Thus, instead of focusing on
important tasks our brain is dispersed and
unfocused.
Let’s inspect the mistakes we make while
working
and learn how to carefully manage
our attention.
Mistake №1 – trying to keep everything in
your head.
Every bit of information not written or
otherwise stored on an external device takes
up room in our short-term memory and
steals our attention.
Our brain is an
extremely powerful tool and it can process a
lot of information, but it cannot store the
vast amounts of information we pour into
our brains.
Usually we do not write down
simple tasks such as “Buy some bread” or
“Call travel agency” but instead try to
remember them all.
This leads to tense
moments when you are trying to figure out
what exactly you have forgotten
or trying to
recall it right now, distracting yourself from
current work.
Solution:
1. Write down your tasks and goals. This will
allow you to free up your memory and make
you more organized.
2. Put all your meetings on your calendar as this will allow you to receive notifications about upcoming events.
3. Make shopping lists before going shopping.
4. Write down all your ideas, as they tend to disappear into subconsciousness .
and when they reappear, they may seem new to you
Mistake № 2 - imprecise wording of your tasks.
Whenever you open your organizer and see a note “Mary”, you are most likely going to think what exactly
you have meant by this note and which Mary it refers to. Making your notes too short makes your brain to work harder.
On the other hand, a very  long note leads to procrastination.
Word your notes properly.
1. The task you are writing down should be simple and contain one specific step.
2. Use brief and clear wording.
3. Be sure to state the action you must complete.
Mistake №3 – accumulation of unfinished tasks
We constantly keep thinking about things we have not done, such as unread letters, unfulfilled promises, phone calls not made
– we keep thinking about these tasks and this creates tension, brings us anxiety and steals our attention.
We often tend to feel guilty for our procrastination and that adversely affects our self-control.
Solution:
1. Solve simple tasks as soon as possible.
2. Set  deadlines for all of your tasks
3. Create checklists of all unfulfilled tasks and work on them
4. If you decide that you do not want to do a certain task – cross it out
of your list so that you feel better about it and are able to move on.
5. Organize and clean up your workplace, computer and e-mail.
Now let us talk about mistakes that are more serious.
Mistake № 4 – Multitasking
Though it is true that most of us can manage several different tasks at the same time,
our brain can only focus on one particular task.
Multitasking makes us less productive, we make more mistakes and it often causes more stress throughout the workday.
You also spend more total time on your work as any
distraction causes you to spend 10-15 extra minutes to regain your concentration.
Nevertheless, we love multitasking as it offers an illusion of productivity.
Solution:
1. Remind yourself that multitasking only hurts your performance, especially when it comes to mental work.
2. Concentrate all your attention on one task during a fixed time period
3. Make other people aware of your being busy
4. Minimize the amount of possible distractions; turn off all unimportant notifications on your phone and computer.
5. Try not to accumulate too many important urgent tasks that will distract you from your current work.
Mistake № 5 – Overwhelming your brain with information.
Nowadays we often face enormous amounts of all kinds of information
and often it is not important for us.
Excess information decreases your ability to concentrate as well as your cognitive abilities.
Solution:
1. Learn to filter the information you receive and critically observe whether you really need it.
2. Use different kinds of adblocks in your browsers.
3. Clean up your email subscriptions, leave all the unnecessary groups and chats in messengers.
4. Set up a time limit for your internet sessions and control yourself.
Mistake № 6 – Work overload
Working long hours without any breaks, mental work during periods of biological decline, working in night – all these
factors tend to decrease your performance and decrease your work speed as well as increase chances of burnout.
Solution:
1. Remind yourself that your brain needs some rest. Quality rest can only be
achieved via long sleep or moderate physical activity and change of activity.
Work in short cycles of 20-25 minutes. In this lecture’s appendix
I have shared my favorite technique – The Pomodoro method.
3. Take quality breaks.
4. Keep your sleep schedule.
Finally, Mistake № 7 – Internal distractions
An important part of your attention resource is being here and now.
We, however, often tend to think about past, present and future tasks and problems at the same time.
Solution:
1. Keep asking yourself what is important at the moment. Keeping track of
your current priorities helps you to concentrate on your goals.
Work on your emotional state. Negative thoughts and feelings can easily capture you entirely
and distract you from your work, as we always tend to think about things that worry us the most.
Analyze your emotions carefully and control your mood.
3. Do not forget to praise and reward yourself for your accomplishments. We all need some sort of stimulation to keep us motivated.
Probably you think that it requires a lot of effort to manage your time, energy and attention effectively.
However, it is only true in the beginning, as quite soon new methods
and ways of managing your time will turn into habits and it will make your life a lot easier.
The best reward for your efforts will be your outstanding results.
Good luck!