Good afternoon dear students.
Today our lecture will be devoted to time management.
During several decades the main point of time management has been
considered in finding ways to do more things in less time.
But in the modern world the key value is not
intensity of our work, but the results we achieve.
This requires us to organize our work in the most efficient way,
managing not only our time, but also our attention and energy.
The very first step towards high performance is to determine tasks that
we should invest our time, energy and attention in.
What is actually important for you, does it correlate with your values, and will it lead you to your goals?
Performing what tasks will influence your results the most?
There are a lot of tools for defining your priorities;
you may find information on them in this lecture’s extra material.
Today I would like to familiarize you with perhaps the easiest, yet very effective, technique that is called “The rule of three”.
The method consists of three steps:
Step 1: In the beginning of the day ask yourself:
“When this day is over, which three things I want to be done?”
Step 2: Write them down
Step 3: You should focus your attention on these three things during the whole day.
- DO NOT include very little things in this list, but do not set undoable goals as well.
- Along with such tasks as “Finish a chapter of my course project” or “Make a presentation”,
do not forget to include your personal things, such as meeting a friend or reading 30 pages of a novel.
If they correlate with your values and bring you satisfaction, they should be in the list.
So, we have determined WHAT should be done in the first place in order to achieve good results.
Now we should figure out AT WHAT POINT during the day we should do our priority things, and when - everything else.
Most likely you have noticed that your energy level fluctuates considerably during the day.
One of the most powerful means of increasing your productivity is to get a clear understanding of your biological rhythm.
In this case you will have a chance to accomplish your tasks with maximum
efficiency when you have your biological peak and you are full of energy.
A large research proved that our level of energy in different periods of the day not only
determines how easily we accomplish a task, but also how well we do it, our ability to be focused.
This is why we should choose carefully when to do things of different complexity and importance.
Let’s have a look at the energy curve of an average person:
We start from biological peak:
it is the part of the day when we are bright and cheerful, have clear mind and high level of energy.
It is the best time for complicated analytical work,
requiring maximal focus of attention and ability to think critically.
Then, usually after midday, level of energy starts to decrease,
the mood often sinks, and the signs of fatigue start to appear.
The best idea would be to give yourself a break to recharge your batteries,
but if you don’t have such opportunity, this time would be good enough for tackling technical tasks, such as
checking your inbox, making phone calls, checking your social media, google some information, and so on.
Of course, what you should do and when do not depend on you completely.
But if you get such opportunity, you should choose respective
part of the day to deal with tasks of different importance and complexity.
As a result, you will experience considerable increase of your productivity.
Now I would suggest you to make a research that will let you analyze
effectiveness of your time management.
Enclosed you will find a table for timekeeping that will help you with several things at once:
- Firstly, it gathers statistics on your actual time use
- Secondly, it measures fluctuation of your energy level during the day
- Thirdly, it helps you to track accomplishment of your priority tasks.
Perhaps, you think that you already know how you spend your time.
Trust me, after a week of keeping this diary you will be surprised.
Monitoring your time and energy is a tiresome task, but the reward will be worth it.
In the end of each day answer the questions under the table.
Also, you should assess critically what you do during the day.
Perhaps, your day looked like a fire extinguishing and you just couldn’t
make it to the cherished three things?
Calculate how much time you spend on things with low or zero efficiency, such as
checking your social networks, chatting in messengers, watching series, and so on.
Think which things of low efficiency you can and should say “no” to.
Let’s recall the key recommendations of this lecture:
1. Analyze your values, needs and goals
2.  Define your priorities. Think which tasks will have the biggest effect on your results.
3.  Each morning write down three key goals for the day and be focused on them during the day
4.  Keep weekly tracking of your time and energy fluctuations during the day
5.  Determine periods of your biological peak and decline
6.  Deal with the most complicated and important tasks during your peak period
7.  Complete the tasks with low output in other periods
8.  Analyze your timekeeping table and take your findings about every previous day into account
9.  Calculate how much time you waste and say “no” to the most malicious “time-killers”
10.  Plan your time and do things deliberately.
See you at the next lecture!