Hello, this video lecture in the section of self-realization
will be dedicated to such an interesting and extremely useful phenomenon as networking.
What is networking?
Those who know English will easily translate this term as "weaving networks",
networks that are  professional and useful.
In fact, this process, as a whole, is what it is.
Networking is a social professional activity
aimed at solving various life’s tasks
with the help of a circle of friends and acquaintances.
In simple words, networking is about creating a circle of different people around you
as well as the ability to maintain a relationships with these people so
that you can always reach their advice, assistance,
promotion of ideas or projects, and valuable information.
The benefits of networking are hard to underestimate.
So let us talk about how to network in a right way
and what pay attention to.
Let us start with considering where it is most appropriate to use it.
First of all, if we are talking about creating our own professional circle of communication,
it is of course, various thematic events:
professional clubs, master-classes, scientific conferences and business training sessions,
depending on your area of interest try to choose those events
that may be of interest to you and bring together specialists from a particular area in one place.
So, for example, if you are an IT specialist,
it makes sense for you to pay attention to and attend
for example,  IT-forums, conferences,
where leading IT companies are represented,
open days and other open events of leading technical universities,
such as, for instance, ITMO University.
Attending these events,
remember the basic networking rules.
Be open and friendly
and ready for new acquaintances,
be sure to be stocked up on business cards,
and keep them handy to build on
your new acquaintance with the exchange your contact information.
Set aside your cell phone and other gadgets for another occasion.
If you hide your eyes in your mobile screen,
you will hardly be able to meet the right person and start a conversation.
Usually, the vast majority of participants in professional events
are open to new acquaintances and conversations,
and that's the reason many people come for.
Therefore, you should bravely come and get to know each other
using the already acquired self-presentation skills,
which we’ve talked about in previous video lectures.
Ideally networking is a mutually beneficial process.
Therefore, it is very important to remember that
while getting to know someone of interest to you,
you should in turn think about “how I could be helpful?”
and the answer to that is your short self-presentation speech.
It is sometimes called Elevator Pitch
or elevator presentation.
Your short, carefully rehearsed speech
in a limited amount of time (usually no more than 1 minute)
just the time that an elevator ride takes.
The peculiarity of the presentation in the elevator is
that within 1 minute you need to tell them who you are,
what you do, what you are interested in,
and how could you be helpful for your counterpart.
Moreover, you need to choose the words in such a way
that they will be understandable and reflect the main point.
So you have a homework to do.
Before you start a thoughtful, purposeful networking,
you need to prepare 3-5 short self-presentations
that you will be using when getting acquainted with people you are interested in.
During the conversation, remember to keep the format of a dialogue,
try to talk with your conversationalist on an equal.
Ask open questions, and do not go to long monologues.
It is important to remember that if you meet people,
take a few business cards, exchange contacts on social networks
and forget about it safely it will be of little use for you.
You need to continue communicating with people you've recently met
so that networking will be as effective as possible.
If you have found the person you really need and interested in,
if you have properly represented yourself,
and you are people with common interests,
you'll always find a reason to arrange a meeting to continue the dialogue.
I would like to say a few words about web networking.
It is based on six degrees of separation theory,
which is that all the people of the earth
familiar with each other through 5 other people.
This is 6 degrees of communication.
You have probably faced this theory in practice.
In many social networks, when you're looking at someone else's interesting profile,
you can see a list of mutual friends
through whom you can potentially meet this person.
It is this section of common friends that can be a key element of your online or web networking,
with which you can make a useful
and mutually beneficial acquaintance with a person you are interested in.
So, we can say that networking is a way of life.
The right environment gives motivation.
Other people's experience and tips significantly shorten the way
to solving your problems and achieving your goals
and the assistance you provide may bring additional dividends in the future.
Having learned the basic principles of networking,
using the basic skills of self-representation,
which my colleagues and I have shared with you in previous video lectures,
you can easily make interesting and mutually beneficial acquaintances.
Be professionals,
surround yourself with professionals
and create an interesting world around you!