Good afternoon dear students.
Today we start a series of lectures, devoted to business and scientific ethics.
First mini-lecture will be devoted to business communication ethics.
We will discuss what business communication is,
what types of business communication exist,
and what rules need to be followed while having business correspondence,
phone discussion and communication in social networks.
So, what is business communication?
In a nutshell, business communication
is interaction in professional environment
for dealing with work matters or tasks.
To make business communication effective
and generally reasonable,
one should follow several rules:
First of all, any communication should have its goal,
and all participants should be interested in it.
For example, it could be negotiations,
signing an agreement,
establishing relations, or an event organization.
Second condition of business communication is observing business etiquette,
subordination, professional roles,
and formal boundaries.
Under formal boundaries I imply
compliance with various protocols, regulations,
as well as simple necessity to control your emotions
and respect your partners and colleagues.
So, efficient communication.
This is how it works:
Firstly,
we need to choose
right means or channel of communication.
Secondly,
you should stick to particular format,
fitting into this channel of communication.
Thirdly,
you should also abide by universal rules,
such as respect, literacy, benevolence,
kind attitude towards your colleagues and partners.
Believe me, compliance with formal and informal rules of business communication
makes interaction with people much easier
and creates comfortable environment at work with your colleagues.
Life hack:
if you initiate business communication,
it is your task to choose channel of communication,
for example, business correspondence,
and suggest it to your partner or colleague.
In the opposite situation, when your colleague has sent you a request,
for example, in form of email,
you should support this choice of communication channel,
and reply in the same style and form.
There are several kinds of communication channels.
In fact, all of them may be divided into four groups.
First one is related to communication
that requires personal presence of all parties.
For example, it can be personal face-to-face discussion, such as an interview.
It can be a group meeting, such as a staff meeting or negotiations.
It can also be individual
or group speech in front of an audience,
such as a presentation.
Second group is interactive channels of communication.
These are emails, phone calls,
various social networks or messengers.
Third group is personal static communication.
For instance, you leave a small note on your colleague’s table.
And final group is impersonal static communication static communication,
such as a report on a project.
All these kinds of communication are different,
but all of them go through several stages.
Preparation for communication may be considered as first stage;
at this stage you define a goal and tasks of future communication for yourself,
gather information and work out behavioral strategy.
Second stage is planning.
Of course, some business meetings or phone calls may happen spontaneously,
but nowadays ability to have a clear action plan
is a considered to be common courtesy and attribute of true professionalism.
It means that you agree on time and place of a meeting
or report submission in advance;
you think out what you are going to say or write,
which arguments will state;
and you also understand what you are aiming at,
and what result you will get.
And final stage,
typical mainly for first two groups,
is a discussion of relevant issues and working out of some decisions.
during phone conversation, business correspondence
and business communication on social networks and messengers.
Smart business discussion over the phone
is a complicated and very important means of communication,
and it has its own peculiarities.
Your opponent at the end of the line cannot see your mimics,
gestures, emotions and generally how you look.
This is why verbal communication becomes especially important.
I mean, what you say and how you say it.
Unfortunately, many people make some common mistakes
that reduce efficiency of business discussion over the phone.
What kind of mistakes are these in particular?
An untimely call,
a call without consideration of time differences,
especially if you talk to the colleagues from other countries,
not concerted call time,
when you just did not agree on particular time,
you call, and your opponent is out of the coverage area or simply cannot speak at that moment.
Another important mistake
is poorly thought-out conversation plan.
Trust me, silence or mumbling irritates a lot.
So, what rules of business phone communication are there?
First – and the most important –
is to greet your opponent and introduce yourself,
of course, if it’s not you colleague
that you talk to everyday.
Also, when speaking Russian, psychologists
recommend to use “Dobry den’” as greeting, instead of “zdravsvuite”,
just because the latter word has too many consonants
that complicate perception of the word.
Also, try to avoid phrases “good morning” or “good evening”,
just because it is assumed
that business communication is held during daytime.
Life hack:
What if the call went dead?
If your phone call goes dead in the middle of conversation all of a sudden,
the one who initiated the call should call back.
Second rule: do not apologize or speak about bothering your opponent.
In the beginning of the call many people say:
“Excuse me for bothering…”,
don’t do that.
Just because from the very beginning
you cause rejection,
anxiety and displeasure in your opponent.
Also, you should not apologize for wasting time of your opponent in the end of conversation.
It will show him/her that you:
a) do not value his/her time;
b) are not self-confident.
Much better to use gratitude phrases,
such as “thank you for your time”.
Life hack:
smile!
Seriously, try to smile more during your phone conversation,
even though the opponent cannot see you.
In fact, your smile and positive emotions
give respective intonations to your voice.
It becomes more attractive, magnetic;
no one wants to talk to a depressive person,
who is unhappy with the work
and doesn’t even try to conceal it.
You should have learnt a lot about business correspondence from previous lectures,
this is why I will just shortly mention
main important ethical points of electronic correspondence.
So, it is worth mentioning
that email is usually used to establish initial contact,
meaning for sending an enquiry.
Also, the rule of mutual respect
should work during electronic correspondence.
This means that you should allow your opponent
to choose time for reply.
However,
all business emails should be replied during one,
maximum two days.
If you are away during longer period,
you should use automatic reply system,
and let people know until
when your will not be able to check your emails.
So, here are the rules of business electronic correspondence:
First of all, I strongly recommend
you to create a separate email address for business purposes.
Usually business email address includes the name of the organization
where you work or its domain,
and your first and last names.
Please,
do not use “-ish” words,
nicknames, your birth year, and so on.
You should not send your CV to a company
that you would like to get employed at
from email address donut1995@mail.ru.
I have a good advice for you:
you may always create an email address on itmo.ru domain.
Secondly,
you should always start your email with an address to some particular person,
or use “Dear colleagues”.
Your email should not be unaddressed.
Also, your signature with your name and contact details
should be stated in the end of your email.
Do not forget to fill out Theme field.
Also, if you have a long chain of email,
and Theme field includes multiple “Re:Re:Re:Re”,
you may stop this chain,
and start a new one, and quote main points
of previous conversation.
If you send an email with attachments,
please,
mention this in the text of your email.
Also, attachments should be named clearly,
so that the addressee could easily understand what’s in there.
When you are ready to send your email, please,
read it once again,
or even twice.
Because simple literacy
is not just a big bonus to your professional image,
but also a sign of respect to your opponent or colleague.
And in the end of this lecture I would like to mention some rules of communication in social networks.
Ethics of communication in social networks and messengers is not explicit.
However, there are several generally accepted and used rules.
Firstly, remember that your profile in social networks is your public image
that your colleagues, supervisors, and potential employers
can see to gather some information about you,
or, for instance, to initiate informal communication.
“Oh, this one is a cat lover, and that one has a country house in Sestroretsk”
… so try to create your positive image in social networks.
Secondly, as a rule, social networks and messengers are used by colleagues
who are on good terms and communicate frequently.
Alternatively, social networks can be used while working on some short-term projects,
requiring constant communication.
One should not write to a superior colleague in social networks first.
Thirdly, try to write briefly.
Format of messengers itself does not imply long texts.
Also, try to avoid using expletives
or generally useless words.
Do not neglect formatting and editing functions.
Remember that it is still business communication, and you need to write grammatically right.
Another important rule:
do not send messages outside regular office hours.
For business communication social networks should be used only in office hours.
Just because, unlike email,
they have format
implying permanent staying in touch.
This is why we can receive and see these kinds of messages 24/7,
and getting a work message early in the morning or late in the night is not pleasant.
And the last life hack:
Do not write down or make any serious decisions
in a social network or messenger conversation.
There are personal meetings, negotiations
or, in a pinch, electronic correspondence for this.
If you discuss some important project in messenger,
you should additionally write down main points
in a separate email.
This is the end of our lecture.
Thank you for your attention!
Remember, following these rules of business etiquette
will make your life easier and more comfortable.