Hello, my name is Natalia Ten and I am a PhD student and a teacher at ITMO University.
Our course is completed by the seventh module called “Tools”.
Here, as we can see, we have collected the most widespread
and useful tools to improve your Soft Skills.
First of all, we will discuss presentations and public speaking.
The outcomes of your work that you are going to demonstrate on a screen in front of an audience.
In the lecture about slides we will talk about presentation structure for science conferences
and about how to work with its content correctly.
You will learn more detailed information about presentation design in the next lecture.
We will tell you how to correctly choose a font, presentation colors
and how to catch an audience’s attention with visuals.
For instance, if you have a motivational or a sales-oriented speech.
Also, we will teach those who like unorthodox software
how to make a presentation with the help of such tool as Prezi.
And of course, we will share the easiest way to make a presentation
if you already have an article written on TeX.
Obviously, with the help of LaTeX document preparation system.
Besides that, we can show you an interesting instrument,
which will help you work with ease with an article’s bibliography -
with the bibliography reference managing program “Mendeley”.
We are sure this tool will make putting together a literature list for your articles easier.
We will also tell you about clouds, more exactly, cloud data storages
and how cloud computing can be useful.
We will also introduce you to the tools for teamwork organization.
You will get to know services which help keeping all the deadlines,
increasing team’s efficiency and productivity and tracking tasks.
We invite you to our course. Good luck!