So, we continue
discussing publications.
A scientific article is
a text that describes your
research and discusses
your results.
Thus, let us suppose that you’ve
conducted a research and want
to share your results and
findings with the rest of the world.
What would you begin
writing article with?
First of all it is important for
you to understand that working
on article is
a long process.
It is impossible to write
a good research article
in a night, a day or
in a few hours before
submitting it
for a publication.
That is why the first thing
to think of is formulating
a working title
of your article.
You’ll understand the
final title of the article
when you complete
working on your text.
The working title, in
its turn, will help you
follow the planned direction.
It would also be beneficial
to formulate the list of
key words at this stage.
The next aspect to consider
is the journal where you will
submit your article
and the potential
readership.
Please be conscious
while choosing a journal,
this choice cannot be random.
Before submitting
your manuscript to one or
another journal you
need to read articles
published there previously.
This would help you imagine
your potential
reader, and the course of your
narrative, your research’s description,
the choice and interpretation
of terms would depend on it.
Every journal
also has
its requirement to
articles’ format,
number of characters
and bibliography.
After you’ve formulated
your article’s working title,
chosen a journal and
imagined your potential reader,
you are able to start
working on your text.
You need to have a detailed
plan, structural parts of
which represent different
parts of your article.
This means that your plan would
include introduction, methods,
results, and discussion/conclusion,
abstract, bibliography
and appendices.
You need to work on all the
parts of your plan simultaneously.
This is a sort
of brainstorming.
And you need to write down everything
that comes to your mind, everything
you want to tell about.
At this stage you shouldn’t
concentrate on your text’s
form – you should
think of the content.
After you fill in all the
parts of your detailed plan,
please leave it
aside and come back to
it in a
day or two.
When you are back the real
editing of your text will
start.
You will be reading and
re-reading your article, adding
and removing something.
This cycle should repeat
itself for a number of
times until there
is nothing else to
remove from your text.
A paragraph is a structural
unit of a scientific
and any other text.
A paragraph starts with an
introduction followed by the main phrase,
supporting facts and conclusion.
Paragraphs are connected by
prepositions, conjunctions,
introductory words and speech clichés.
You need to edit your
language and register
after the text of
your article is ready.
Please get rid
of filler words –
these are the words
that have no sense or
structural
function.
It is also necessary
to get rid of repetitive
lexical units and lexical
constructions, if any.
Also, it is not common
to use a pronoun
“I” in Russian
academic writing.
You’ll have to use “we”
or “authors” instead,
even if you
made research
on your own.
I will tell you more
about register and grammar
when writing in English
in the next lecture.