Hello everyone, my name is
Daniil, and we are about to start a new module
devoted to scientometric
indicators.
Scientometrics is a comprehensive research
field that studies
and assesses not only journals
and individual scientists,
but also research
organizations and
the science itself based on
quantitative methods.
There are dozens and hundreds of different
scientometric indicators.
We will discuss only
the basic ones.
Particularly those that are
related to individual
scientists.
Here there are three main metrics.
First one is total number of tests and total
number of publications of a particular
researcher.
It is usually assumed that the more citations
you have, the more
demanded you are.
The more publications you have, the more
productive
scientist you are.
However, this metric has
one key drawback.
First of all, as
the time goes it may only increase,
which is logical, because as you develop your   scientific career,
you write more and more articles, and get more
citations; having said that, it is not
quite correct to compare
young scientists with
the distinguished ones,
because the latter
would have much higher
metrics.
Second indicator is evaluation of citations
number
of the author's most cited publication.
Why is this needed?
For instance, your scientific career was very short
or during your academic path you have
just published
a couple of monographs and
articles, which
nonetheless have dramatically
changed
your research field.
Most likely, it will
gain big number of citations,
but if to use other
scientometric
indicators, it will not be seen.
Therefore, we are talking about him
always separate.
This is why we always take this
one into consideration.
Hirsch index is a metrics
that was suggested
in 2005 by an Argentine American
physicist Jorge Hirsch from
University of California
in San Diego.
This is an attempt to balance
qualitative
and quantitative evaluation of
scientist's works.
But in reality
it fails in both.
H-index is calculated the following way: your
h-index amounts to n
if you have n number of
publications, each of which
was cited at least n
times.
For example,
if your h-index is 5, it
means that you have
written 5 articles, each of
which was cited at least 5
times.
Congratulations.
As a rule, when we talk about h-index,
we have to mention several
key drawbacks of this
metrics.
First of all, it does not consider input of each
particular
scientist in joint work.
Let's say that there is a big research
group that
works at the Large Hadron Collider
and writes an article, and there is you.
And you have been writing
your monography for several years.
In both cases, citations
for one member of the
group and for you,
as an individual author, will
always amount to an arbitrary unit.
This is not always correct.
Secondly, h-index ignores those scientific
fields
that are not presented in the form of
classical reports
or conferences, publications or
reviews.
For instance, if we consider modern
technologies,
patents are usually the way to
report and demonstrate
scientific activity in the
field.
Or perhaps, there are some books and
monographies that are not very well indexed
in scientometric data bases.
Thirdly, and we have mentioned this before, h-
index
ignores your most cited and important
articles.
For example, if you have
written only
three works, and one of them is
cited dozens or thousands of times, your
h-index
will still be 3.
On the other hand, you could
have written fifteen
articles of fair quality, and each of
them would be cited at least fifteen times.
In this case you h-index would amount to 15.
But in reality you have not influenced  significantly
to your research field.
Moreover, besides h-index per se,
there are several h-index-like indicators.
Scientometricists have a joke that another h-
index-like
indicator is invented every second
week, and they do not monitor
them anymore.
Nonetheless, m- and g-indices have fitted in
more or less.
M-index is same h-index
that additionally
considers length of
scientific career or, to put it
differently, that very
time period over which the scientific works in   consideration
were written.
Thus, it enables to balance young and
experienced scientists.
and already experienced at the academy
person.
G-index compensates for another significant
drawback of h-index, and considers input of
your
most cited
articles.
It uses concept of
average citation index.
Furthermore, there are so called specialized
h-indices.
Biologists have their own h-index,
biological
index;
physicists have their own as
well; and so on.
Why is it needed?
It is an attempt to balance
difference in citations
across scientific fields.
The point is that, on the one hand, there is
molecular
biology, as actively developing
field, with
many articles being published
and cited.
Thus, h-indices of researches in this field
will increase actively
and promptly.
On the other hand, there is mathematics
and mathematicians publish their articles much  rarer,
preferring monographs to publications.
They also cite each other seldom.
This is why, on average, their h-indices will be  lower than
those of biologists, yet their input
in science per se might not
differ.
For this reason, the field-specialized  indicators
are used.
Nevertheless, it is worth mentioning that,
despite all
its shortcomings, h-index is the
most well-known
indicator that is widely used
in the whole
scientific community.
Generally, it is a good attempt to balance
quality
and quantity, but we should
understand what actually
stands behind these numbers.
For all the shortcomings of the Hirsch index,
this is one of the most
common indicators that have taken root in the   scientific community.
It is widely used by scientists, and you can often
see it in the beginning or in the end of
presentation of a particular
scientist.
It is a rather good attempt to balance quality
and quantity, but we should understand what
actually stands behind these numbers.
At the following lecture we will talk about those scientometric
indicators, which are used
for particular articles
and journals, and which are used for evaluation of
universities activity.