Hello, this is Natalya Khokhlova.
We are continuing to move forward to our dream job.
Today we are going to talk with you about the second stage
of the selection of candidates for most of the existing vacancies.
This stage is the stage of interviewing.
You have probably already studied the previous lecture
in which one we have talked about
creating your CV/
You have taken into account all our recommendations
and as a result you have such a unique resume,
after reading which your potential employer
has decided to get to know you better.
Now you can expect a call.
A company representative will call you soon
and will set an interviewing date.
Keep in mind that this call is not just a formality,
but can result in a phone interview,
which will be an intermediate stage
between your CV and personal meeting.
That is why you need to be
well-prepared for this stage.
So, try to provide optimal conditions for your call.
Make sure, that there is no ambient noises and distraction
so you can learn all the information
you are provided with and ask questions.
Sometimes the interviewing is held
in a written form by email.
In this case, watching our lecture
about business correspondence and
considering the main principles of a business letter,
you can safely organize your interviewing
in such a way of communication.
So, you already have a date, time and place
of your future interview.
What to do now,
how to act,
how to prepare
and what to pay attention to?
The major part of your success
depends on your level of preparation.
Before the meeting  try to find out
as much information as possible
about the company, what the company does,
what clients and partners it has,
what growth opportunities it has,
its development plans,
what requirements the company presents
to candidates for vacancies that are available.
And what is the most important,
try to find out all possible information
about your vacancy.
Analyze once more time
what kind of your knowledge and skills
could be useful for a company.
Having examined the company in turn
you may find out how it could be useful for you
and how it can be of interest
to you professionally.
Your appearance is an important part
of a successful interview.
The proverb “clothes make the man”
is the best approach.
Conservative style will be appropriate.
But there we need to note,
that if your work implies working with people,
communicating with clients and partners,
you should opt for more formal style of clothes.
On the other hand,
if you are applying for some kind of creative job,
you should not adhere to the formal clothes.
Imagine, however, how frustrating it can be
when you tell your conversation partner about
some very important professional achievement,
but they don’t listen to you
reading the inscriptions
on your T-shirt instead,
translating them or trying them on
to see if they fit you in some way
or if they may somehow belong to a recruiter.
Thus, T-shirts with inscriptions
should be put aside for another occasion.
As for other meetings,
, arrive to your interview on time.
It will be optimal to come
10-15 minutes earlier.
It will be good if you have
contact information of the person
you are going to meet.
Then you'll be able to inform them
if you arrive too early
or are being late.
The most important rule
during the conversation
is the rule of honesty and openness.
Remember, the interview is the process
where both participants
are interested in the outcome.
You're interested in getting this job.
Your counterpart is interested
in filling the vacancy,
finding a decent and professional candidate.
Therefore, if you plan to find
a job for yourself,
if you plan to work in this company
for a sufficient amount of time,
it is sensible to speak openly
about your knowledge, your skills
and to voice your expectations
from the company.
Do not be afraid to ask questions.
You can ask some clarifying questions
and it wouldn’t be redundant
even to take a notebook and a pen
to take some notes.
Answering questions try to avoid
simple answers, such as “yes” or “no”.
However, very detailed answers
in the format of a monologue
are also better left
for a more informal conversation.
Remember, not only you
want to know more about the company,
but also a company wants to know you.
At the end of interviewing
it is vital to discuss the feedback.
Usually,  professional recruiters
say it by themselves,
when and in which way
they will contact you
– by phone or e-mail.
If for some reason
you have not been told this information,
you can clarify it by yourself.
The most important thing to remember
when interviewing is
that in any case, you win.
You either get invaluable experience
of self-presentation and passing interviews,
or you get the dream job.
I wish you good preparation,
decent vacancies and interesting interviews.
Good luck and see you
at our next video lectures!