Good afternoon!
My name is Yulia Manaeva.
I’m teaching a course
called Effective Team Management
at ITMO University.
Today we are going to discuss public speaking skills.
Right now you might have assumed
that you’ll encounter public speaking very rarely
or not at all in your career.
But that is not true,
because every time we are trying
to communicate an idea to a group of people,
we are actually taking a role
of a public speaker at that moment.
So, if at some point in the future
you are asked to say a toast
during your parents’ anniversary,
or to ask your employer for a raise,
you’ll have to rely
on your public speaking skills.
So, if you are doing a public talk,
how do you start preparing for it?
Do you start with listing the contents of your talk?
Actually, no.
No need to reach
for your laptops and notebooks for now.
Content of the talk is an important part,
but not the one to start your preparation with.
A good starting point
would be asking yourself: Why?
Why am I giving this talk?
What will change after it?
? In other words:
What goal am I trying to achieve with this talk?
An answer to this question
will help you to choose the style of your talk.
There are a lot of different styles,
but I’m going to focus on just one of them.
For example, there are motivational talks
and exposing talks
which are politicians’ favorite genre.
There're manifestos with philosophical postulates,
gratitude speeches, ceremonial speeches,
that, for example, may serve as entertainment
if spoken at a party.
At last, there is a persuasive speech
and its goal is to fully convince listeners
with your thesis.
But don’t make the mistake
of making just an informing speech.
There are a lot of information sources
surrounding us nowadays,
Attending a talk just to get information
is not a very effective way to get some information.
That’s why you have to make it
a bit more difficult for yourself
by setting a goal of getting at least some people
to read more about the topic on their own
after listening to your speech.
Or as an alternative you can show
how a very difficult topic can be structured
and distilled to its core,
so that it becomes accessible to an untrained listener.
In other words, if you select the right goal,
your speech will be powerful
and will have a direction,
and these are the most important things
for a public speaker!
Well, now you know the goal of your speech!
But that is still not enough
to go to the contents.
The next question
you have to answer is: Who?
Who are the people
that will be listening to you tomorrow
or in the next few days?
It is good to know your audience’s
average age and profession
as well as to what extent
they are proficient in your topic
and the level of their interest in you as a speaker.
You need to take into account
historical, national and ethnic details.
In order to make sure that the jokes
you have chosen and the events
events you are going to mention
would be perceived adequately.
It is also nice to know
the time of the day
when your speech is scheduled.
Because the audience in the morning
or after a hearty lunch, or tired audience
in the very end of a business event
are three different audiences.
However, you need to make sure
you do everything to switch the audience’s attention
from their inner processes to you.
So, now you know the purpose
of your presentation and your audience.
And we finally proceed to the content.
I do not recommend writing your speech
sentence after sentence.
First of all, because the written speech
is always different from oral.
It is a real torture to listen to a lecture
of a professor who reads aloud a book
instead of retelling the material with his own words.
No matter how wonderful are the citations
you’ve chosen, what allegories
and metaphors you’ve found,
there is a high probability
that you will be too nervous and forget all of them.
In this case it is more important to remember
the structure of your talk,
know the main points that must be mentioned.
You should understand what sequence of ideas
will bring you to your speech’s goal.
If you still opt for writing your speech
sentence after sentence,
make sure that the phrases you use are simple.
Do not overload your sentences with participles.
They are hard to be spoken and understood.
Make sure you have an introduction,
main part and conclusion
when you have finished your talk’s draft.
Introduction is the very chance
to make a first impression
that is not provided to us twice.
That means your start should be bright,
confident and dynamic.
Look at the most prominent speakers of our time.
What tools do they use in order
to concentrate the attention on themselves?
You could start with a rhetoric or practical question
that opens a dialog with your audience.
For example, “Who has ever snoozed
their alarm clock in order to have
another five more minutes before finally waking up?”
Another good approach is using statistics.
The numbers always attract attention.
For example, 85% of managers confess
they feel lonely at work.
The technique, by the way, can be strengthened
by making the audience you story’s objects.
In this case you can formulate the phrase like this:
according to the Health Association
every fourth person in this room suffers from insomnia.
You will feel the change
in your audience’s energy instantly.
Because the majority of your listeners
is now really interested in what you are talking about.
Different jokes, parables and life stories
also suitable if they take you to your speech’s goal.
You can start with self-presentation
if your personality or professional area
are connected to your topic.
You can make a promise,
thereby intriguing the public
Promising to take everyone
from point A to point B.
The media sources are also suitable.
For example, movie clips, documentaries,
audios that you could demonstrate
without making any comments.
This will give more tension
to what happens on the stage.
So now that you are sure
all the attention is yours,
you can proceed to the main part of your talk.
This is the part that allows you
to deeply study each thesis and argument
that you have prepared.
If this is a convincing speech,
the specialists suggest to distribute the arguments
supporting your main thesis as follows:
Start with a bright and strong argument
that would drag the audience’s attention.
The second argument could be a bit weaker,
as if it is said in order
to make the quantity of arguments larger.
And the third one should be
a very strong and emotional one,
the one that would prepare your audience
to the culmination of your speech.
There, by the way, you can summarize
all the arguments and formulate
your key idea once again.
You should do it as bright and strong
as possible for your listeners to remember it.
Then you can proceed to the conclusion.
The conclusion is as important
as the introduction.
After all, the aftertaste
that will remain with the audience
after you leave the stage depends
on how you finish your talk.
Many methods of completing a speech
mirror those techniques
that we spoke about in the introduction.
You can ask your audience a question
that they would reflect on alone.
You can also finish your speech with a joke,
real life story, call to action, promise,
conclusion or morality.
Media sources would do as well
a video game excerpt, an audio, documentary
or a movie scene that illustrates
what has just been said on a stage.
Well, looks like we have done
preparing for a public talk.
One important stage is left.
And this is a rehearsal!
Find someone to listen to you.
A person who is ready to tell you
a tactful and true feedback about how you give a talk.
It would be good if you manage
to model at least minimal degree of worry,
which soon you will be feeling on the stage for real.
Why?
The thing is, that, being overwhelmed
by our feelings and emotions,
we tend to change the way we speak
and instead of using those beautiful citations,
allegories and methaphors
we start to use filler words, awkward silence,
clumsily filled pauses and the “Ehhh”.
You need to know your enemy
in order to not let it happen!
When you have information
about which repetitions you tend to have,
what filler words you use mostly,
you will be able to pre-select the necessary phrases,
lexical chunks and syntactic tricks,
in order to hide the moments when the right word
is not in your memory.
With this the preparation
for the verbal part of your speech is done.
Still, there are some non-verbal aspects.
We are going to talk about them
in the next lecture.
See you soon!